<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to the clergy of the diocess of Norfolk and Suffolk wherein they are desired to challenge the Quakers once more to meet them in the face of the country in order to prove which of them are Christ's ministers which may be done according to the method herein laid down with very little disputation and to the great satisfaction of the auditory / by a member of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>S. J.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B22946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F864AC</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37812</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17021880</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17021880</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105834</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B22946)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105834)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1464:29 or 1615:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to the clergy of the diocess of Norfolk and Suffolk wherein they are desired to challenge the Quakers once more to meet them in the face of the country in order to prove which of them are Christ's ministers which may be done according to the method herein laid down with very little disputation and to the great satisfaction of the auditory / by a member of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>S. J.</author>
                  <author>Field, John, 1652-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: S. J.</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to John Field, Quaker.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>This item appears as Wing F864AC at reel 1615:24 and as Wing J33A (number cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.)) at reel 1464:29.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105834:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105834:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A <hi>Letter</hi> to the <hi>CLERGY</hi> OF THE Dioceſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Suffolk,</hi> Wherein they are Deſired to Challenge the <hi>Quakers</hi> once more To Meet them in the Face of the Country, in Order to Prove which of them are <hi>Chriſt's Miniſters;</hi> which may be done according to the Method herein laid down, with very little Diſputation, and to the Great Satisfaction of the Auditory.</head>
            <byline>By a Member of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </byline>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Being at <hi>Weſt-Dereham, December</hi> the 8th laſt, expecting to have heard a <hi>Diſpute,</hi> though it proved little but <hi>Noiſe,</hi> only a few Charges you made againſt the Old <hi>Quakers;</hi> by which it appeared, you had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Object againſt the preſent Generation of them, yet Charged them all down-right with <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> which you pretended to prove out of their Books, moſt of the Authors being in their Graves; ſome of whom have been Dead theſe Twenty or Thirty Years, and bringing not one Quotation or Inſtance of a late Date againſt them, out of any of their Books, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member; tho' it ſeems they have lately Wrote much, which I, with many more of the Country, thought very ſtrange, that you ſhould be ſo Laviſh in your Charges againſt them (moſt of whom you knew not, and could prove nothing againſt them preſent) which might well make Mr. <hi>Archer</hi> ſo far to do them Juſtice, as to ſay, <hi>they were Orthodox.</hi> That which the <hi>Quakers</hi> inſiſted on, I with many more, both of our <hi>Church</hi> and others, admired at, and thought it very unreaſonable in you to deny, which was <hi>a Copy of the Quotations out of which you pretend to Prove your Charge;</hi> tho' at the ſame time they proffered to pay for it. The laſt Day I was not there, neither have heard any thing to purpoſe was done, ſaving you Baited them with your <hi>Bugg.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105834:2"/>
            <p>I conceive your Deſign was, to Prove their Religion falſe, by your Reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beforehand on <hi>Meaſures,</hi> whether the <hi>Quakers</hi> would meet you or no: But I conceive you might have taken a better Way, which is this; <hi>Firſt,</hi> To Prove your own <hi>Religion</hi> True, and your <hi>Selves</hi> Chriſt's Miniſters; and then you do not only prove the <hi>Quakers</hi> falſe, but all others that ſeparate themſelves from you: Perhaps you'll ſay, there's no need of that, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> hath been proved to be the <hi>True Church</hi> many Years and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ago; does that Prove you to be <hi>Chriſt's own Miniſters</hi> in theſe Days? And if you ſhall Evade it, and ſay, Who can diſprove us to be <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt?</hi> I confeſs, I am not willing to go about that, yet muſt tell you, There are many in this <hi>Nation,</hi> and that of our <hi>Church</hi> too, which do greatly Queſtion that Point, <hi>Whether you be Chriſt's Miniſters?</hi> Therefore I ſhould think it abſolute Neceſſary for you to Prove your Selves ſuch, if you can, and that may End all Differences, and bring all into One Mind again. But perhaps you may think, that will cauſe a long Diſpute: But I'll tell you a Way to do it without Diſpute, and it will be ſoon done; I hope you will own that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were <hi>Chriſt's Miniſters,</hi> and Preached the Right and True <hi>Goſpel,</hi> according to the Mind and Will of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> alſo, hoping you will allow, that <hi>Chriſt's Miniſters</hi> do Preach the ſame in this our Day, as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did in their Day: For the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to be very Strict concerning the <hi>Goſpel</hi> which they Preached, ſaying, <hi>Tho' we, or an Angel from Heaven, preach any other Goſpel unto you, than that ye have received, let him be accurſed,</hi> Gal. 1. 8. And the Apoſtle being ſo Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive of the Need of that Advice (as though he had ſpoken to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Preachers) comes over with it again in the next Verſe.</p>
            <p>Now my Maſters, Let me ask you one Queſtion, by Reaſon you call your ſelves <hi>Chriſt's Miniſters,</hi> What is the Right and True <hi>Goſpel</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle preached? And I do not only put the Queſtion to you, but to all thoſe that call themſelves <hi>Chriſt's Miniſters:</hi> For why? None other can anſwer it Rightly. I find two ſorts of <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> the Firſt are <hi>Chriſt's Miniſters,</hi> that received their Authority as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Not of Man, neither by Man, but by Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father:</hi> The Second are the pretended <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> theſe are they that receive their Authority of Man, and by Man; of which I deſire your Serious Conſideration: Can you ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>you have received your Authority not of, nor by Men, but by Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father:</hi> But if you have not, how are you <hi>Chriſt's Miniſters?</hi> The <hi>Goſpel</hi> you ſee is but One in every Age, <hi>If we, or an Angel from Heaven, preach any other Goſpel unto you, than that which we have preached, let him be accurſed:</hi> Does not this diſtinguiſh enough between the two ſorts of <hi>Miniſters?</hi> But <hi>Chriſt</hi> further puts the Difference, <hi>Many will ſay to me in that Day, Lord, Lord, have we not Propheſied in thy Name, and in thy Name have caſt out Devils, and in thy Name done many Wonderful Works?</hi> Mat.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105834:2"/> 7. 22. And in another place, <hi>We have Eat and Drank in thy Preſence, and thou haſt taught in our Streets: But he ſhall ſay, I tell you, I know not whence you are, depart from me all you Workers of Iniquity:</hi> Theſe are they that Preach in <hi>Chriſt's Name,</hi> and do many Notable Works in his <hi>Name;</hi> yet you hear <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>He never knew them:</hi> That is as much as to ſay, He never ſent them: Why, who ſent them then? They are ſent from the <hi>Schools of Learning,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their ſending they muſt not Preach, if they have not their Authority from theſe great <hi>Schools;</hi> as St. <hi>Paul received it from Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father,</hi> they muſt not be received (Pray unfold theſe Contradictions if you can) this <hi>Scholarſhip</hi> was all laid by with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and nothing accounted on by him, tho' he had as much of it as ſome of my Maſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being brought up under <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> a Great Doctor in that Day: And <hi>Chriſt</hi> tells <hi>Paul,</hi> That <hi>he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to him on purpoſe to make him a Miniſter,</hi> and tells him what he is to do, <hi>To open the Blind Eyes, to unſtop the Deaf Ears, to turn them from Darkneſs to Light, and from Satan's Power to God,</hi> Acts 26.</p>
            <p>Now as <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> bare Teſtimony againſt the <hi>Man-made Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> in that Day; ſo the Lord commanded his <hi>Prophets</hi> to cry in the <hi>Word of the Lord</hi> againſt the <hi>Hireling Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> under the Law, that Preached for <hi>Pieces of Bread</hi> and <hi>Handfuls of Barley,</hi> he declared, <hi>I have not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they run; I have not ſpoken to them, yet they propheſied. But if they had ſtood in my Counſel, and had cauſed my People to hear my Words, then they ſhould have turned them from their Evil Ways, and from the Evil of their Doings,</hi> Jer. 23. 21, 22.</p>
            <p>Now Sirs, to return to my Queſtion, perhaps you'll ſay, This <hi>Goſpel is Glad Tidings of a Saviour;</hi> that I grant is part, but there goeth ſeveral other Rights with it, which leave out any one of them, and it's no more the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> than the <hi>Trinity</hi> is the <hi>Trinity,</hi> leaving out One of the <hi>Three Perſons;</hi> leave out any One of the <hi>Rights</hi> which the Apoſtle preached, and you leave out the <hi>Power;</hi> then what good can it do? The Apoſtle tells you what the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is, <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>for it is the Power of God unto Salvation,</hi> Rom. 1. 16. ſo he again tells them, <hi>Our Goſpel came not unto you in Word only, But alſo in Power, and in the Holy Ghoſt, and in much Aſſurance; as ye know what manner of Men we were among you for your ſake,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 1. 5. The ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Which things alſo we ſpeak not in the Words which Man's Wiſdom teacheth, but which the Holy Ghoſt teacheth,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 13. So you may ſee the <hi>Goſpel</hi> which Chriſt's Miniſters preached, made ſome Work where it went, as the Preaching of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> in <hi>Macedonia,</hi> where the Heart of <hi>Lydia</hi> the Lord opened, and a <hi>Damſel</hi> poſſeſſed with a <hi>Spirit of Divination,</hi> that brought her Maſters much Gain by her <hi>Soothſaying,</hi> cried out, ſaying, <hi>Theſe Men are the Servants of the moſt High God, which ſhew unto us the Way of Salvation; and this did ſhe many Days,</hi> Acts 16. But mark the Event, when the Spirit was come out of her, that her Maſters ſaw that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105834:3"/> the Hope of their Gain was gone, then they began to cry, <hi>Help Rulers, Help Magiſtrates</hi> (but they had not a Parliament to Cry to, as our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have) theſe Men being of a different Religion, do exceedingly Trouble our City, and Teach Cuſtoms which are not Lawful for us to Receive, neither to obſerve (why, what's the Matter now? They were for a free Miniſtry I warrant you) and they, the Maſters, that had ſuch Gain by this Spirit of Divination; had the Magiſtrates and Multitude ſo far at their Beck, that the Magiſtrates cauſed many Stripes to be laid on theſe <hi>Goſpel Miniſters,</hi> beſides a Priſon they had ready.</p>
            <p>We ſee it was the Loſs of their Gain, that made that Bitter Cry, <hi>Help Rulers, Help Magiſtrates:</hi> Now, pray my Maſters let me privately ask you one Queſtion in your Ears, for you will hardly openly Confeſs it (leſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Body ſhould compare you with the foregoing Maſters) are not you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of your Gain alſo, that you have made the ſame Cry? Are not you afraid of your Fat Benefices, your Darling Tithes? If you ſay Nay, yet the People do, and will, Judge that's the Sore Place you Kick at. So, Sirs, by theſe things you may ſee, the Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt</hi> do a great deal of Good where they go; and that the pretended Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt</hi> can do None, becauſe they know not the Goſpel of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ;</hi> neither can they, except it were Revealed unto them by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Sirs, to my firſt Requeſt, Prove your Selves Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and you do your Buſineſs all at once; for the doing thereof, Pleaſe to take the Advice of Chriſt, who ſays, <hi>The Tree is known by its Fruit, and by their Fruits you ſhall know them:</hi> In Order to which, ſeeing you were once ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to Challenge the <hi>Quakers</hi> to Meet you; to <hi>Hollow,</hi> and <hi>Hout,</hi> and <hi>Bait</hi> Them; Let me, my Dear Maſters, beg it of you, that you would appoint once more, both Time and Place, and Order the <hi>Quakers</hi> to Meet you in the Face of the Country, and bring ſome of your <hi>Fruits</hi> with you of both ſides; perhaps ſome of you have been ſettled Men in your Pariſhes, ſome 10. 20. ſome 30 Years or more, which if you be <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Miniſters,</hi> there is no doubt but you have much <hi>Fruit</hi> in all this Time; if you bring but Two or Three out of every of your Pariſhes, according to Chriſt's ſaying, <hi>Out of the Mouth of Two or Three</hi> Witneſſes <hi>every Truth ſhall be Eſtabliſhed:</hi> Bring in ſuch as are able to give in Teſtimony before God and the Country, that your Goſpel came to them with ſuch Power, that it hath turned them from <hi>Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God:</hi> Then theſe are become your Witneſſes, that your Goſpel is the True Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and your <hi>Fruit</hi> to be good, and ſo the <hi>Tree</hi> good alſo. This is the Way the Apoſtle took<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>We Preach unto you the Goſpel of God, ye are Witneſſes, and God alſo, how Holily, and Juſtly, and Unblamably we behaved our ſelves among you:</hi> 1 Theſ. 2. And alſo ſpeaking of the Truth of the Goſpel which is come unto<note place="margin">☞</note> you, as in all the World, and bringeth forth <hi>Fruits,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105834:3"/>
            <p>Now, Sirs, bringing theſe Witneſſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they do not only prove you to be <hi>Chriſt's Miniſters,</hi> but it will take off thoſe Scandals which are thrown upon you by the Country: Let me go where I will, you are all Charg'd with one thing or other amiſs; ſome with <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> ſome with <hi>Pride,</hi> ſome with <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> indeed what not? For moſt Folks will have one Story or other to tell of a Parſon; perhaps you'l ſay that's no New thing, the Great Lord Jeſus was called a <hi>Wine-bibber,</hi> a <hi>Friend to Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sinners;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> was called a <hi>Sinner,</hi> and a <hi>Babbler<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> But, Sirs, remember this, thoſe that accuſed Chriſt and his Apoſtles, were not of the ſame Society or Communion with them, they were Unbelievers; but theſe that accuſe you, are Men of our own Church, which you muſt and do own, by making them Communicants with you; and ſurely one would think you would not give your <hi>Sacrament</hi> to any but Believers, and only ſuch as are Worthy too: Remembring <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words, <hi>He that Eateth and Drinketh Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, Eateth and Drinketh his own Damnation.</hi> Therefore appear, the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>You</hi> once more, and bring ſome of the beſt of your <hi>Fruits</hi> with you, to Teſtifie what Tree you are of: Then you may have ſomething to tell the King and Parliament of; but till then you will be look'd upon to be but like <hi>Demetrius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and the reſt of his Crafts-men, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. that were ſo Ingenuous to confeſs their Gain was in Danger, if the True Miniſters of Chriſt were ſuffered to Preach up and down.</p>
            <p>What would you have to ſay, if the King and Parliament ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the ſame Anſwer back upon you, that Chriſt did to the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they brought the Woman before him, <hi>taken in Adultery, in the very Act<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> You did not take theſe Men in the very Act; Neither can you lay any ſuch thing as you Charge them with, to their own particular Charges, yet you would willingly Hang them for it, Right or Wrong (only the good Old Proverb is made good, <hi>Curſt Cows have Short Horns<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>) Chriſt did not ſo by the Woman, but ſaid, <hi>He that is without Sin amongſt you, let him caſt the firſt Stone at her, and they went out all of them, and left the Woman where ſhe was,</hi> and as ſhe was: Would you do ſo, if the King ſhould return the ſame anſwer back upon you? If you did not, you would be worſe than thoſe Unbelieving <hi>Jews;</hi> what if I ſhould ſay, you are worſe than the <hi>High Prieſts</hi> were in Chriſt's Days, that accuſed him before <hi>Pilate,</hi> for they had no Example before Them; you were not their Example, but methinks they might be yours, Remember what Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Saul,</hi> when he was a Perſecutor (who did it out of more Zeal, than I fear you do) <hi>Why Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuteſt thou me:</hi> And ſaid in another place, <hi>He that doth it to the leaſt of theſe, doth it to Me;</hi> I think you have not prov'd theſe Men, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Quakers,</hi> to be falſe Preachers, if you have, pray tell us when, and how you did it? We expected you would have done it in Print, and that with all Expedition; which would have been more Serviceable to your Cauſe, than a Blind Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105834:4"/> which gives no Certain Knowledge of any thing, and will only ſerve to pleaſe the Simple and Ignorant of our Church; as <hi>Toys</hi> do Fools and Children, the moſt material of which, is not the Matter, But the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Names which are to it.</p>
            <p>Sure if your <hi>Corner Story</hi> you ſpeak of, gave ſuch full Satisfacton and Proof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the <hi>Auditory</hi> to Cry out <hi>Blaſphemy, Blaſphemy!</hi> It might have been Extraordinary Encouragement for you to proceed in your Proofs, and that in the Face of the Sun, which would look more Honourable for you, than a Blind <hi>Corner Story,</hi> which I know not any heard but your Selves.</p>
            <p>The <hi>High Prieſt</hi> had a <hi>Judas</hi> at work for Mony, to Betray Chriſt into their Hands, one that was a Follower of Chriſt that betrayed him for Mony: Have not you a <hi>Judas</hi> at work now, for Mony, to Betray the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers?</hi> One that was a Follower of Them; pray where is the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two Traytors? Why, the Difference is Twofold, the Firſt was a <hi>Iudas,</hi> the Latter a <hi>Bugg. <hi>Secondly, Judas</hi>
               </hi> had Thirty Pieces of Silver which was paid by the <hi>High Prieſt;</hi> the Latter had his Mony not only from the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> but a Recommendation alſo, not only to the Leſſer <hi>Prieſts</hi> throughout the <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> but the <hi>Laity</hi> were deſired to Contribute to ſo Good a Work.</p>
            <p>And now, Sirs, he is made a Serviceable Prop to our Church: But now I Remember my ſelf, there is another thing in which theſe two Traytors differ'd: Notwithſtanding, <hi>Judas</hi> had made his Bargain for Thirty Pieces of Silver, when he had done his Work, Horrour and Condemnation ſo ſiezed him, that he brought back the Mony, ſaying, <hi>He had betrayed the Innocent</hi> (which the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Thoſe</hi> with him, little mattered when the Work was done, but ſaid, <hi>See thou to that) and went and Hanged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;</hi> which ſhews his Sorrow and Regret; Is there Sorrow and Regret in the Latter? We muſt leave Events to Him that is Higher than the Higheſt; I would not meddle too far in that, but deſire the Conſideration of all, that if he ſhould come to ſhow any Remorſe on that Nature, whether they do not think he might Meet with the ſame Treatment his Brother did; I ſhall further ſay, 'tis the End that Crowns all.</p>
            <p>Now, Sirs, a little further to conſider, do the <hi>Quakers</hi> hold Errors? How do you know it? You are not competent Judges: You ſay you are full of Rottenneſs. from the Crown of the Head to the Sole of the Foot, there is no Soundneſs in you. Chriſt forbad ſuch Judging in theſe Words, <hi>Thou Hypocrite, firſt caſt out the Beam that is in thy own Eye, then thou ſhall ſee clearly the Moat that is in thy Brothers Eye:</hi> Have we not a Vulgar ſaying, <hi>The Kettle calls the Pot Black?</hi> You know your ſelves to be as Black within as without; and ſo confeſs your Selves, and your Crimes, to be ſuch, in your daily Actions; and for you to Charge them, looks ſtrange; you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105834:4"/> might Remember the Words of St. <hi>Paul, Thou that ſayeſt a Man ſhould not Commit Adultery, doſt thou Commit Adultery? Thou that Abhorreſt Idols, doſt thou Commit Sacriledge?</hi> Rom. 2. 22. Or as if he had ſaid, Thou that ſayeſt a Man ſhall not Blaſpheme, and doſt thou Blaſpheme? You Charge the <hi>Quakers</hi> with <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> and is not that yery Charge <hi>Blaſphemous?</hi> In ſaying, <hi>The Light within, as taught by them, leads them into theſe, and many more Errors.</hi> Is Chriſt the Author of <hi>Blaſphemy?</hi> You have now Charg'd it upon him with a Witneſs, if we believe the Teſtimony of the Holy Scriptures, in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of himſelf, who ſaid, <hi>John 8. 12. I am the Light of the World, he that followeth me ſhall not walk in Darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of Life.</hi> See Luke 2. 32. He was given for <hi>A Light to Enlighten the Gentiles, and the Glory of my People Iſrael.</hi> See <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 34. and 16. 8. <hi>John</hi> 1. 7, 8, 9. All Points out Chriſt to be the <hi>Light;</hi> So that, Sirs, you have not only Charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Quakers,</hi> but Chriſt too, as high as you Charge them: Was he ever Charged higher when Perſonally on Earth? Tho' he was then ſo Charg'd, pray who was it by? By the <hi>Prieſts</hi> I'll warrant you, <hi>Matth. 26. 65, 66. What further need have we of Witneſſes? Behold, now you have heard his Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, what think you? They anſwered he is Guilty of Death:</hi> What think you my Maſters of thoſe People that gave Sentence, <hi>He is Guilty of Death?</hi> Was not this like your <hi>Corner Story</hi> of the Peoples Satisfaction? From which they cried out <hi>Blaſphemy, Blaſphemy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> You call Chriſt your Maſter, and your Selves His Miniſters; If you be ſo, I hope you will Obey his Commands; if you think the <hi>Quakers</hi> are the <hi>Tares,</hi> and your ſelves the weighty <hi>Wheat</hi> (which the People will and do judge) you ſhould let them grow together till the <hi>Harveſt,</hi> the End of the World, <hi>and in the time of Harveſt, I will ſay to the Reapers,</hi> &amp;c. but you would not let them grow together, if you could help it; Do not you Contradict <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Words? And yet call him <hi>Maſter;</hi> he ſays, <hi>He will ſay to the Reapers;</hi> you ſay, you will do it your ſelves: By this he muſt not do his own Buſineſs, but you will do it for him (like Hanging of Men for God's ſake) There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by this, pray who is Maſter, <hi>Chriſt</hi> or <hi>You?</hi> That you are ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to do his Work for him, and ſuch Work as he hath forbad you; is it your great Love to <hi>Him,</hi> or your great Envy againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> that you cannot abide them any longer in your ſight, if you could help it?</p>
            <p>Perhaps you'll ſay, The <hi>Quakers</hi> made this; I tell you the <hi>Quakers</hi> knew no more of my Writing it than your ſelves; for I am no <hi>Quaker,</hi> nor I think I never heard them Preach Six times in all my Life; but this I can ſatisfie you of, that I have heard them but Twice theſe Six Years: Neither have I joined my ſelf with any other <hi>Religion,</hi> but with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and if you come to Prove your ſelves <hi>Chriſt's Miniſters,</hi> I ſhall then never Forſake you, but Love and Reſpect you as ſuch: But if you do not, nor cannot, then I muſt remember the Words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105834:5"/> where he ſaith, <hi>There ſhould come ſuch, having the Form of Godlineſs, but deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Power thereof, from ſuch,</hi> I muſt, <hi>turn away:</hi> If you do not Meet, and bring ſuch Witneſſes, as aforeſaid, I muſt with many more conclude You to be the Men the Apoſtle ſpake of, <hi>that are in the Form of Godlineſs, but denying the Power;</hi> therefore I dare do no other than <hi>Turn away from you;</hi> though you pretend you have ſtop'd the <hi>Gangrene,</hi> except you take effectual Care, the old Sore, being falſly Healed, will break out again; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps make the Wound then prove Uncurable, as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 15. 18.</p>
            <p>Now Sirs, I ſhall draw to a Concluſion, deſiring you to take the Advice of Doctor <hi>Gamaliel</hi> in theſe Words, <hi>Ye Men of Iſrael, take heed to your ſelves what you intend to do, as touching theſe Men. Let them alone: For if this Counſel, or this Work be of Men, it will come to nought: But if it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it; leſt haply ye are found even to Fight againſt God,</hi> Acts 5. 35, 38, 39.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I hope you will pardon me for not ſetting my Name at large to this <hi>Letter;</hi> the Omiſſion of which was, becauſe I take you to be in <hi>Cain</hi>'s Envious Spirit, about killing his Brother <hi>Abel;</hi> and for what Reaſon may be eaſily known, becauſe his <hi>Sacrifice</hi> was Accepted, and his Brother's Rejected: I ſee your Envy is ſo great againſt them, you would Hang them if you could; and perhaps you would do the ſame by me (if you knew me) for giving you this Advice.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>If the Man that wrote theſe Lines you fain would know,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then come to me, the Man to you I'll ſhow.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. J.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105834:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
